<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/</id>
    <title>Open Source with SLU Blog</title>
    <updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/"/>
    <subtitle>Open Source with SLU Blog</subtitle>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Global grad Hackathon Ignites Innovation Amongst Future Tech Leaders]]></title>
        <id>hackathon</id>
        <link href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/hackathon"/>
        <updated>2023-11-27T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[18 teams comprising 58 students put all their programming skills to work for a two-hour hackathon that took place on 27th November at Saint Louis University.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>18 teams comprising 58 students put all their programming skills to work for a two-hour hackathon that took place on 27th November at Saint Louis University.</p><p><strong>What:</strong> <br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a>, student in MS Computer Science and graduate research assistant organized the hackathon in collboration with global grad initiative at SLU<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Thursday, September 21 to Friday, September 22 (2 days)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/admission/visit/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saint Louis University</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/slu-hackathon-2023/Get-Started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Problem Statement</a>, <a href="https://www.slu.edu/news/announcements/2023/december/global-graducate-scholars-hackaton.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SLU - Newslink</a></p><p>On Monday the 27th of November, a Hackathon was conducted as part of a project under the Global Grad Initiative. With the support of Dr. Eric Armbrecht, the founding director of the Global Grad initiative, Hackathon was organized by Abhilash Kotha and a dedicated team of 7 other MS students.</p><p>As part of the challenge, all the 18 teams tried to solve a real-time issue of grading scantron answer sheets. Orchestrated with the help of Dr. Kate Holdener and Mr. Daniel Shown, the challenge kept the participants busy for the entire duration. The prize money of $500 will be awarded to the winning team in the coming week once submissions have been reviewed.</p><p>Throughout the day, students collaborated and put their skills to practice, benefiting from the opportunity to solve practical problems and gain hands-on experience. Dr. Holdener and Mr. Shown visited the venue to support the student teams. They interacted with teams and clarified any doubts the students had about the requirements.</p><p>The hackathon concluded with Dr. Armbrecht distributing certificates of participation to the teams and applauding their efforts and engagement. Feedback from participants highlighted appreciation for the practical experience and the motivation they gained from working under such conditions. Describing his experience with the event, one of the participants Ramakanth said,</p><p>“This Hackathon was my first technical competition ever. Throughout the intense 2 hours, I learned so much from my teammates about collaborating under pressure to tackle a complex real-world problem. I am looking forward to more such events”</p><p>Any promising solutions produced as part of the students can potentially be used by Open Source with SLU in building an open source software product that automatically grades scantron answer sheets. </p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Mr. Daniel Shown explaining the requirements" src="/assets/images/daniel-fa493f96d02a9aaf6e444a7aec74b269.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash kotha with Dr. Eric armbrecht" src="/assets/images/eric_and_abhilash-acf5ef5d35548978022908a32fe34790.JPG" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Participants busy solving the problem" src="/assets/images/participants-db59cae88e77d2a48975178828c2f437.JPG" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="One of the teams recieving a certificate" src="/assets/images/certificates-25b5881e24c92afe0ee70a73eb75967f.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Abhilash Kotha</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/AbhilashKotha</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
        <category label="news" term="news"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Strange Loop Conference]]></title>
        <id>strange-loop</id>
        <link href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/strange-loop"/>
        <updated>2023-09-21T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[The last Strange loop conference took place in Saint Louis this September and our students got the great opportunity to volunteer for the event. It was a unique experience for our students.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last Strange loop conference took place in Saint Louis this September and our students got the opportunity to volunteer at the event. It was a unique learning experience for the students. </p><p><strong>What:</strong> Strange Loop Conference<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sailikhita-pulijala/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sailikhita Pulijala</a>, MS students in Computer Science along with a few other students volunteered at the conference<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Thursday, September 21 to Friday, September 22 (2 days)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.thestrangeloop.com/venue.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Union Station, Saint Louis</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://www.thestrangeloop.com/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strange Loop Website</a></p><p>Strange Loop is an annual technology conference that gathers innovators,
researchers, and professionals from diverse fields to explore and discuss emerging
trends, cutting-edge technologies, and unconventional ideas. The conference held
in St. Louis, Missouri, featured a wide range of topics, including programming
languages, web development, artificial intelligence, distributed systems, and more.</p><p>Abhilash Kotha and Sailikhita Pulijala, second-year Master's students in Computer Science and Research Assistants with Open Source with SLU along with a few other students from the department had an opportunity to attend the event as volunteers. They not only contributed to the success of the event but also gained valuable experience in the process.  The two-day conference was full of opportunities for students. A few students were at the <a href="https://dgtized.github.io/lemniscate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lemniscate sculpture</a> created by  <a href="https://annjohnson.art/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ann Johnson</a> and <a href="https://github.com/dgtized" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Charles L.G. Comstock</a> explaining the participants about the sculpture and answering any questions they had. The volunteers also assisted the organizers in distributing the merchandise and facilitating the book signing event on the second day of the event. They were able to connect with representatives from SafeStack, Strava, Swimm, Vonage, Improving, Capital One, Flexiana, John Deere and many other companies about their newest inventions and products.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash and other students with Charles L.G. Comstock, one of the creators of the strange loop lemniscate sculpture" src="/assets/images/1695328700073-fb60cc3c833cc611c7541173fc5e49d2.jpeg" width="1170" height="878" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Lemniscate sculpture" src="/assets/images/lemniscate-15e460e63b85e319297d2c026c7689a0.png" width="1124" height="1334" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Abhilash Kotha</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/AbhilashKotha</uri>
        </author>
        <author>
            <name>Sailikhita Pulijala</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/LikhitaPulijala</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
        <category label="news" term="news"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Elementary OS Workshop]]></title>
        <id>elementary-os</id>
        <link href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/elementary-os"/>
        <updated>2023-09-16T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[We launched first monthly open source software workshop at the SLU Library's ATC. Students got a hands-on practice creating and using a portable Linux. It was a great success that exceeded the expectations of all the planners.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We launched first monthly open source software workshop at the SLU Library's ATC. Students got a hands-on practice creating and using a portable Linux. It was a great success that exceeded the expectations of all the planners. </p><p><strong>What:</strong> Elementary OS<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> Presentedy by <a href="https://yashb196.github.io/yashb196/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yash Bhatia</a>, MS student in Computer Science<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Friday, September 15<br>
1:30-2:30 p.m. (1 hour)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/library/services/academic-technology-commons/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pius Library, ATC</a><br>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1QhlBWzoqiha1X8AogqNqMb4jynmaEDOAU2xmdrFD3Cc/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">presentation of instructions</a></p><p>A group of students and staff huddled over laptops around a large conference table in the Academic Technology Commons of Saint Louis University's Pius Library. The sound of 3D printers hummed in the background. On an already busy Friday afternoon these students had elected to spend their time getting some hands on experiences with open source software. </p><p>Yash Bhatia, a second year Masters student in Computer Science and a Research Assistant with Open Source with SLU, handed out USB flash drives and printed instructions. Then he went <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1QhlBWzoqiha1X8AogqNqMb4jynmaEDOAU2xmdrFD3Cc/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">step-by-step</a> with students down the path of creating a bootable flash drive with <a href="https://elementary.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">elementary OS</a>. Elementry OS is a distribution of the Linux OS that touts itself as "The thoughtful, capable, and ethical replacement for Windows and macOS". Yash then walked those attending the workshop through actually using the flash drive they created as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Live_USB" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">portable operating system</a>. This is a technique where the user can plug and play the entire system on any desktop computer. He walked the group through a variety of use cases for a portable OS, and showed some of elementaryOS's capabilities as a portable operating system.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Yash introduces elementary OS" src="/assets/images/20230915_003-8171ecc2dfc0647f654c323fb571e37a.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Students working together" src="/assets/images/20230915_001-2881c26eb854d018bc0ee7c8cf383aaf.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Yash explaining details" src="/assets/images/20230915_005-5012907a674e05044f954a2405745e39.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Students all around the table" src="/assets/images/20230915_002-914320b911fe98ddc238a0e4d9112faf.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Yash assisting staff learning about OSS" src="/assets/images/20230915_004-1be527d5a895b5254d5a9dbff750aa3c.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="3D printers printing in the background; possibly still printing the same job today." src="/assets/images/20230915_000-bb10edb6d9d7a467176d4f3bcf5138a1.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Shown</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/kungfuchicken.com</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
        <category label="news" term="news"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[OSSci Panel Discussion - Accelerating Scientific Discovery]]></title>
        <id>ossci-panel-discussion</id>
        <link href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/ossci-panel-discussion"/>
        <updated>2023-07-10T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Members from Open-Source Science (OSSci) were at Saint Louis University and our students had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members for discussion.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Members from Open-Source Science (OSSci) were at Saint Louis University and our students had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members for discussion.</p><p><strong>What:</strong> Hackathon<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a>, student in MS Computer Science and graduate research assistant at Open Source with SLU and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rajukarmuri731/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raju Karmuri</a> alumni and tech lead at Open-Source at SLU were part of the discussion panel<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Monday, July 10 <br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/admission/visit/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saint Louis University</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://opensource.science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OSSci Website</a></p><p>Students had an incredible time as they had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members at the Open-Source Science (OSSci) event at St. Louis University! It was an inspiring conversation about accelerating scientific discovery through open-source science. Panelists Tim Holy, Alexy Khrabrov, Patrick Cuba, Abhilash Kotha, and Raju Karmuri had engaging discussions that shed light on many important topics the audience liked their conversation on how to bridge the communication gap between science and technical communities with more education and training, and how open source could help that.</p><p><a href="https://medium.com/open-source-science-initiative/st-louis-university-july-10-panel-discussion-accelerating-scientific-discovery-2285eb2bfb60" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ossci Newsletter</a></p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Discussion panel" src="/assets/images/panel-c02f3492ba9943aba3b94b4cb280278c.jpg" width="1400" height="1091" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Abhilash Kotha</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/AbhilashKotha</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
        <category label="news" term="news"/>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Starting Up]]></title>
        <id>starting-up</id>
        <link href="https://oss-slu.github.io/news/starting-up"/>
        <updated>2022-07-01T00:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Saint Louis University Computer Science Department starts and open source program office with a generous $704,482 grant from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Saint Louis University Computer Science Department starts and open source program office with a generous $704,482 grant from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</p><p>More details on our start can be found in <a href="https://www.slu.edu/news/2022/april/open-source-software-center.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SLU Newslink</a>.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Daniel Shown</name>
            <uri>https://github.com/kungfuchicken.com</uri>
        </author>
        <category label="announcement" term="announcement"/>
        <category label="news" term="news"/>
    </entry>
</feed>