<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Open Source with SLU Blog</title>
        <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/</link>
        <description>Open Source with SLU Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Pi4Micronaut - A new recipe from Open Source with SLU]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/blog_pi4micronaut</link>
            <guid>blog_pi4micronaut</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Pi4Micronaut, a library by Open Source with SLU for Micronaut, enables development on Raspberry Pi. Version 1.0 was released in the Maven repository on Pi Day.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Is it a 'Pi'e? Yes, we made a recipe named <strong>Pi4Micronaut</strong> with the base of Java using the ingredients like Micronaut and Pi4J. This is baked at Open Source with SLU research lab and served hot on a Raspberry Pi. Today, 3.14, we released version 1.0 into the Maven repostiry. Confused? Let me explain what is this all about.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Baking Pi4Micronaut at Open Source with SLU" src="/assets/images/Baking_Pi4Micronaut-f9171aefedc7e8b1908517c729bb14a1.png" width="2938" height="1959" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>Welcome to the world of Pi4Micronaut, a powerful Java library designed to simplify the interaction between Java developers and electronic components connected to the Raspberry Pi. Here, we are going to explore features, benefits, and how to get started with Pi4Micronaut.</p><p>Pi4Micronaut is versatile and can be employed in various real-world scenarios. Some use cases include:</p><ul><li>Home Automation</li><li>IoT Projects</li><li>Educational Purposes</li></ul><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-this-is-started">How this is started?<a class="hash-link" href="#how-this-is-started" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>This project came to life with the collaboration of Open Source with SLU and Unity Foundation. Working with electronic components on the Raspberry Pi using Java has its challenges. Pi4Micronaut aims to address these challenges by providing  an efficient way for Java developers to interface with hardware connected through GPIO extension board.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="why-should-you-use-pi4micronaut">Why should you use Pi4Micronaut?<a class="hash-link" href="#why-should-you-use-pi4micronaut" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>It's hard to write functionalities for an electronic components like LCD's, RFID's etc., that you want to control them using your software. We took that hardest part of the job on us and providing you the functionalities of them to directly integrate with your code.</p><p><em>"As a developer, I have struggled to understand how these components actually work, and implementing their functionalities has been the most difficult part of this project"</em> said Adrian Swindle, a student developer at Open Source with SLU, pointing out how hard it is to understand electrical circuits and developing appropriate functionalities to work for a component.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-special-about-pi4micronaut">What special about Pi4Micronaut?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-special-about-pi4micronaut" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We use Micronaut framework that allows us to run a local server on the Raspberry Pi to interact with the components and also provides micro-service architecture. We bind this with Pi4J Library to establish communication with GPIO on Raspberry Pi.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="is-this-a-boon-to-java-developers">Is this a boon to Java Developers?<a class="hash-link" href="#is-this-a-boon-to-java-developers" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Yes, now a days we have a huge reliability on python when it comes to dealing with Raspberry Pi, there are tons and tons of applications that are developed using python. Are you comfortable with Java and want to develop some IOT applications? Don't worry we got you covered.</p><p>To make it easier to incorporate our library into your projects, we have published Pi4Micronaut v1.0 on to the Maven Central Repository. Integrate our library and just call the functions of the components which we made it available for you.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lets-get-started">Let's get started!<a class="hash-link" href="#lets-get-started" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="discover-the-seamless-integration-between-pi4micronaut-and-your-application-enhancing-the-development-which-is-efficient-and-scalable">Discover the seamless integration between Pi4Micronaut and your application, enhancing the development which is efficient and scalable.<a class="hash-link" href="#discover-the-seamless-integration-between-pi4micronaut-and-your-application-enhancing-the-development-which-is-efficient-and-scalable" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Let's dive into Pi4Micronaut library usage by following these simple steps:</p><ol><li>Create your Project using <a href="https://micronaut.io/launch" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Micronaut</a> Framework.</li><li>Add Pi4Micronaut and other dependencies to your project
Ex:  implementation 'io.github.oss-slu:pi4micronaut-utils:v1.0'</li><li>Create a circuit board with electronic components which we provide support for</li><li>Add your configuration details into Application.yml file.</li><li>Create a java class file and implement the functions based on your requirements and call our functions based on the functionalities required for the components which you have setup.</li><li>Build, copy and Run the jar file on Raspberry Pi. Make sure the Micronaut server is up and running.</li><li>Connect to the same network and SSH on to Raspberry Pi to use curl commands.</li><li>Boom! Now you can control your electronic components through your application.</li></ol><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="stay-tuned">Stay Tuned!<a class="hash-link" href="#stay-tuned" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>We are coming up with support for more components and improvements in Pi4Micronaut. We're committed to enhancing the library based on user feedback and community contributions.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="want-to-contribute-to-pi4micronaut">Want to contribute to Pi4Micronaut?<a class="hash-link" href="#want-to-contribute-to-pi4micronaut" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>You are most welcome! Whether you're a hobbyist or a professional, explore the possibilities and contribute to the growth of the Pi4Micronaut community.</p><p>Ready to get started? Visit the Pi4Micronaut <a href="https://github.com/oss-slu/Pi4Micronaut" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a> repository for <a href="https://oss-slu.github.io/Pi4Micronaut/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">documentation</a>, code samples, and more. Your feedback and contributions are highly valued!</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="our-community">Our Community<a class="hash-link" href="#our-community" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li>Thanking Dr. Kate Holdener and Daniel Shown from Open Source with SLU for taking up this initiative.</li><li>Thanking Jeff Brown and Jen Weise from Unity Foundation for providing the technical support whenever required.</li><li>Thanks to our Developers here at Open Source with SLU, community, contributors, and supporters who have made Pi4Micronaut possible.</li></ul><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Pi4Micronaut Team" src="/assets/images/pi4micronaut_team-39ab1c3c91a7a5d84bbb30cc56689f32.jpg" width="3493" height="2850" class="img_ev3q"></p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Pi4Micronaut Team Working" src="/assets/images/pi4micronaut_team_working-22fd56ad49d0ee33ac7d031100392578.jpg" width="3724" height="2241" class="img_ev3q"></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="lets-build-a-future-where-interacting-with-electronic-components-on-the-raspberry-pi-is-simpler-and-more-enjoyable">Let's build a future where interacting with electronic components on the Raspberry Pi is simpler and more enjoyable!!!<a class="hash-link" href="#lets-build-a-future-where-interacting-with-electronic-components-on-the-raspberry-pi-is-simpler-and-more-enjoyable" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What's cooking at Open Source with SLU]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/pi4micronaut</link>
            <guid>pi4micronaut</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We are coming up with a special recipe on the occasion of Pi Day, March 14.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We are coming up with a special recipe on the occasion of Pi Day, March 14.</p><p>Have you ever heard about Pi Day? Let me summarize it for you.</p><p><i>Pi Day is an annual celebration of the mathematical constant π. Pi Day is observed on March 14 since 3, 1, and 4 are the first three significant figures of π.</i></p><p>Here is a fun fact: March 14th is Albert Einstein's Birthday! One of science's greatest minds.</p><p>People across the world celebrate Pi Day by eating pie, hosting fun events, and holding community gatherings related to STEM. But what does this have to do with us? Well, we are contributing our special recipe to Raspberry Pi community.</p><p>We are coming up with a big announcement on Pi Day related to <a href="https://github.com/oss-slu/Pi4Micronaut" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pi4Micronaut</a>.</p><p><strong>Stay Tuned!</strong></p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Baking at Open Source with SLU" src="/assets/images/baking@oss-slu-78173fe77e688bdef28644b09a33fac7.png" width="2938" height="1959" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[The Pioneers of API Testing - Embracing Open Source Tools]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/api-testing-tools-workshop</link>
            <guid>api-testing-tools-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 23 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[List of FOSS API tools that are used in testing REST calls.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I organized and led a successful workshop on API testing tools at the ATC Pius library, where 10 enthusiastic students attended the session and actively engaged in the live demonstration.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Participants at the beginning of the event" src="/assets/images/2024-02-23_1-57b9ee0e703e23dbec77fa2ef3154699.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Participants looked at the screen, fully engaged in the discussion." src="/assets/images/2024-02-23_2-bad6f600cbdf0b9f3e1442fbfde30a3d.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p><p><strong>What:</strong> The Pioneers of API Testing - Embracing Open Source Tools<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> Presentedy by <a href="https://github.com/LikhitaPulijala" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">me</a>, MS student in Computer Science and Graduate Research assistant at OSS SLU<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Friday, February 23<br>
3:00-4:00 p.m. (1 hour)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/library/services/academic-technology-commons/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pius Library, ATC</a></p><p>In this workshop, I showcased several essential tools in the realm of API testing and emphasizes the collaborative nature of FOSS in driving innovation in software development. Below is the brief summary of the contents explained in the workshop.</p><p>In the ever-evolving landscape of software development, the pivotal role of Application Programming Interfaces (APIs) is undisputed. APIs serve as the backbone of digital interactions, enabling seamless communication between diverse software components. Amidst this scenario, the significance of API testing tools, particularly those anchored in the Free and Open-Source Software (FOSS) philosophy, cannot be overstated.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="the-foundation-of-foss-in-api-development">The Foundation of FOSS in API Development<a class="hash-link" href="#the-foundation-of-foss-in-api-development" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>FOSS stands as a testament to the collaborative spirit of the software development community. It offers tools that are not only free to use but also grant users the liberty to inspect, modify, and enhance the source code. This open environment fosters innovation and accelerates the advancement of API testing methodologies, ensuring that developers have access to tools that are both powerful and adaptable to their ever-changing needs.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="exploring-essential-api-testing-tools">Exploring Essential API Testing Tools<a class="hash-link" href="#exploring-essential-api-testing-tools" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The realm of API testing is rich with tools designed to streamline the testing process, enhance collaboration, and ensure the delivery of robust APIs. Among these tools, certain names stand out for their contributions to the FOSS community:</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="postman-the-swiss-army-knife-of-api-testing">Postman: The Swiss Army Knife of API Testing<a class="hash-link" href="#postman-the-swiss-army-knife-of-api-testing" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Postman isn't just a simple utility, it's a complete environment tailored for API development. Its widespread appeal is rooted in its user-friendly interface, catering to both novices and experienced developers. Postman empowers users to swiftly craft intricate HTTP requests, inspect responses, and automate API testing. Through features like collection management, folder organization, and seamless sharing among team members, Postman cultivates a collaborative development atmosphere. Its intuitive design streamlines API creation, sharing, and testing processes, supporting various request methods and providing tools like collections and environments for efficient API management. By facilitating team collaboration, Postman facilitates smoother cooperation among developers working on API projects.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="hoppscotch-a-leap-towards-simplicity-and-collaboration">Hoppscotch: A Leap Towards Simplicity and Collaboration<a class="hash-link" href="#hoppscotch-a-leap-towards-simplicity-and-collaboration" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Once called Postwoman, Hoppscotch emerges as an open-source tool for crafting API requests right from a web browser, sparing users the hassle of desktop setups. Its allure lies in its straightforwardness and broad protocol support, including WebSocket, GraphQL, and SSE, catering to diverse testing needs. Hoppscotch excels as a web app, fostering real-time collaboration and boasting cloud syncing capabilities. Its versatility extends across various environments, making it a prime option for API testing.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="insomnia-streamlining-api-workflows">Insomnia: Streamlining API Workflows<a class="hash-link" href="#insomnia-streamlining-api-workflows" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Insomnia is well-known for its simplistic method in API testing, offering a neat and easy-to-use interface. It's especially beneficial for developers dealing with REST, GraphQL, and gRPC APIs. Its lightweight structure makes it a popular choice for individuals who value quickness and effectiveness without compromising on features. Recognized for its straightforwardness and minimal design, Insomnia is tailored for developers seeking an effective tool supporting request sequencing and prioritizing performance. Its open-source basis fosters community involvement, consistently enhancing its range of features.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="swagger-standardizing-api-development">Swagger: Standardizing API Development<a class="hash-link" href="#swagger-standardizing-api-development" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h3><p>Swagger, alternatively referred to as the OpenAPI Specification, offers a consistent, language-independent method for interfacing with REST APIs. This enables both people and machines to grasp the functionalities of a service without requiring access to source code, explicit documentation, or examination of network traffic. Tools associated with Swagger, such as Swagger UI and Swagger Editor, simplify the process of designing, documenting, and utilizing APIs. Swagger adopts a holistic approach to API testing, with a focus on security, code generation, and establishing norms. It assists in streamlining API governance, guaranteeing adherence to industry best practices and standards.</p><p>Each of these tools brings unique advantages to the table, contributing to more efficient, collaborative, and high-quality API development and testing processes. By leveraging these open-source resources, development teams can not only accelerate their workflows but also ensure that their APIs are robust, reliable, and ready for integration into complex software&nbsp;ecosystems.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="empowering-innovation-through-collaboration">Empowering Innovation Through Collaboration<a class="hash-link" href="#empowering-innovation-through-collaboration" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The essence of FOSS in API testing is not just about offering free tools but about cultivating an environment where innovation thrives through collaboration. These tools, developed and refined by the community, ensure that developers have access to resources that are not only advanced but also adaptable to the unique challenges of API testing.</p><p>In conclusion, as we navigate the intricate web of digital interactions facilitated by APIs, the role of FOSS tools in testing and development becomes increasingly paramount. They not only equip developers with the necessary resources but also embody the spirit of open collaboration that drives the software industry forward.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Exploring Open-Source Alternatives to Everyday IT Tools]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/os-alternatives-workshop</link>
            <guid>os-alternatives-workshop</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[OSS workshop about open source alternatives to everyday tools was conducted at ATC Pius library and it was a great success with 15 curious students joing the session and participating in the live demo.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>OSS workshop about open source alternatives to everyday tools was conducted at ATC Pius library and it was a great success with 15 curious students joing the session and participating in the live demo. </p><p><strong>What:</strong> Exploring Open-Source Alternatives to Everyday IT Tools<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> Presentedy by <a href="https://yashb196.github.io/yashb196/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a>, MS student in Software Engineering and Graduate Research assistant at OSS SLU<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Friday, February 09<br>
2:00-3:00 p.m. (1 hour)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/library/services/academic-technology-commons/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pius Library, ATC</a><br>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://drive.google.com/file/d/1fNDAjl_kqJNfBmhCYkUlR2NOnjWYzf6r/view?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">presentation deck</a></p><p>In a recent workshop hosted by Abhilash Kotha, 15 curious students gathered to explore options in the world of open-source software. The workshop, organized by OSS, aimed to shed light on powerful alternatives to everyday tools like browsers, email clients, text editors, and even API testing tools.</p><p>The focus wasn't just on functionality but on the core values of open-source: transparency, collaboration, and freedom. By using open-source tools, participants learned about the benefits of knowing exactly what they're using, customizing it to their needs, and contributing to a vibrant community of developers.</p><p>The workshop wasn't just theoretical. Abhilash provided a live demo of installing open-source tools directly from GitHub, using their documentation. The audience witnessed the potential of Penpot, an open-source alternative to Figma, and even dabbled with Gpt4all, an open-source interface for open LLM models.</p><p>The energy in the room was profound. Participants actively engaged in discussions, asking questions and sharing their own experiences. It was clear that the message resonated, sparking a genuine interest in the possibilities of open-source technology.</p><i>"I always knew there were alternatives to tools like Chrome and Outlook but was always afraid to try them. I will definitely try them now,"</i> said Rutvik Mannem, tech lead at OSS, highlighting the positive takeaways.<p><img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash looking at the camera while the participants are registering for the event" src="/assets/images/20240209_1-ec4220a1b8a73f7c515a5c3374db7f77.jpeg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash introducing the topic" src="/assets/images/20240209_2-a8a97a6c1e361fffdd8b4193df7ff958.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash giving a demo on Penpot" src="/assets/images/20240209_3-79f6579e6a34c5d85817572f1d26d552.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Innovation Challenge: Raspberry Pi Application for Research Support]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/innovation-challenge</link>
            <guid>innovation-challenge</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 15 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Research labs are filled with real innovation opportunities,  from data acquisition to automation infrastructure. This is your chance to help accelerate discovery.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Research labs are filled with real innovation opportunities,  from data acquisition to automation infrastructure. This is your chance to help accelerate discovery.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="innovation_challenge" src="/assets/images/innovation_challenge-d7bd90080cfc8ac06206922b2252644f.png" width="1456" height="816" class="img_ev3q"></p><p><strong>What:</strong> $500 Innovation Challenge: <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raspberry Pi</a> Application for Research Support<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> Saint Louis University students<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Spring 2024<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/admission/visit/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saint Louis University</a><br>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://forms.gle/r7jb9wb22y1pMqVP9" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sign Up</a></p><p>Get ready to unleash your creativity and make a real impact to SLU research. We're calling all students to participate in a competition to create applications using <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raspberry Pi</a> technology. Your creations must be game-changers for real research labs. Some examples are: replacing manual work with a <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raspberry Pi</a> based automation, using sensors to collect data, alerting on something, achieving something new, etc.</p><p>Here's how it works:</p><ol><li>Form a Team or Compete Individually</li><li>Identify an Opportunity</li><li><a href="https://forms.gle/r7jb9wb22y1pMqVP9" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Propose a Solution</a></li><li>Finalists Announced on <a href="https://www.piday.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pi Day</a></li><li>Build your Solution</li><li>Win Cash and Glory</li></ol><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="deadlines">Deadlines<a class="hash-link" href="#deadlines" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li><a href="https://forms.gle/r7jb9wb22y1pMqVP9" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Proposal form submissions</a> are due by 11:59pm on March 4.</li><li>Finalists will be announced on 3.14, <a href="https://www.piday.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pi Day</a>, March 14.</li><li>Project builds must be submitted by April 22.</li><li>Winners will bew announced at the SSE Senior Showcase, April 24.</li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Global grad Hackathon Ignites Innovation Amongst Future Tech Leaders]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/hackathon</link>
            <guid>hackathon</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[18 teams comprising 58 students put all their programming skills to work for a two-hour hackathon that took place on 27th November at Saint Louis University.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>18 teams comprising 58 students put all their programming skills to work for a two-hour hackathon that took place on 27th November at Saint Louis University.</p><p><strong>What:</strong> <br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a>, student in MS Computer Science and graduate research assistant organized the hackathon in collboration with global grad initiative at SLU<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Thursday, September 21 to Friday, September 22 (2 days)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/admission/visit/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saint Louis University</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://github.com/slu-hackathon-2023/Get-Started" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Problem Statement</a>, <a href="https://www.slu.edu/news/announcements/2023/december/global-graducate-scholars-hackaton.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SLU - Newslink</a></p><p>On Monday the 27th of November, a Hackathon was conducted as part of a project under the Global Grad Initiative. With the support of Dr. Eric Armbrecht, the founding director of the Global Grad initiative, Hackathon was organized by Abhilash Kotha and a dedicated team of 7 other MS students.</p><p>As part of the challenge, all the 18 teams tried to solve a real-time issue of grading scantron answer sheets. Orchestrated with the help of Dr. Kate Holdener and Mr. Daniel Shown, the challenge kept the participants busy for the entire duration. The prize money of $500 will be awarded to the winning team in the coming week once submissions have been reviewed.</p><p>Throughout the day, students collaborated and put their skills to practice, benefiting from the opportunity to solve practical problems and gain hands-on experience. Dr. Holdener and Mr. Shown visited the venue to support the student teams. They interacted with teams and clarified any doubts the students had about the requirements.</p><p>The hackathon concluded with Dr. Armbrecht distributing certificates of participation to the teams and applauding their efforts and engagement. Feedback from participants highlighted appreciation for the practical experience and the motivation they gained from working under such conditions. Describing his experience with the event, one of the participants Ramakanth said,</p><p>“This Hackathon was my first technical competition ever. Throughout the intense 2 hours, I learned so much from my teammates about collaborating under pressure to tackle a complex real-world problem. I am looking forward to more such events”</p><p>Any promising solutions produced as part of the students can potentially be used by Open Source with SLU in building an open source software product that automatically grades scantron answer sheets. </p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Mr. Daniel Shown explaining the requirements" src="/assets/images/daniel-fa493f96d02a9aaf6e444a7aec74b269.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash kotha with Dr. Eric armbrecht" src="/assets/images/eric_and_abhilash-acf5ef5d35548978022908a32fe34790.JPG" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Participants busy solving the problem" src="/assets/images/participants-db59cae88e77d2a48975178828c2f437.JPG" width="4032" height="3024" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="One of the teams recieving a certificate" src="/assets/images/certificates-25b5881e24c92afe0ee70a73eb75967f.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Strange Loop Conference]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/strange-loop</link>
            <guid>strange-loop</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[The last Strange loop conference took place in Saint Louis this September and our students got the great opportunity to volunteer for the event. It was a unique experience for our students.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The last Strange loop conference took place in Saint Louis this September and our students got the opportunity to volunteer at the event. It was a unique learning experience for the students. </p><p><strong>What:</strong> Strange Loop Conference<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/sailikhita-pulijala/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sailikhita Pulijala</a>, MS students in Computer Science along with a few other students volunteered at the conference<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Thursday, September 21 to Friday, September 22 (2 days)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.thestrangeloop.com/venue.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Union Station, Saint Louis</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://www.thestrangeloop.com/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Strange Loop Website</a></p><p>Strange Loop is an annual technology conference that gathers innovators,
researchers, and professionals from diverse fields to explore and discuss emerging
trends, cutting-edge technologies, and unconventional ideas. The conference held
in St. Louis, Missouri, featured a wide range of topics, including programming
languages, web development, artificial intelligence, distributed systems, and more.</p><p>Abhilash Kotha and Sailikhita Pulijala, second-year Master's students in Computer Science and Research Assistants with Open Source with SLU along with a few other students from the department had an opportunity to attend the event as volunteers. They not only contributed to the success of the event but also gained valuable experience in the process.  The two-day conference was full of opportunities for students. A few students were at the <a href="https://dgtized.github.io/lemniscate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lemniscate sculpture</a> created by  <a href="https://annjohnson.art/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ann Johnson</a> and <a href="https://github.com/dgtized" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Charles L.G. Comstock</a> explaining the participants about the sculpture and answering any questions they had. The volunteers also assisted the organizers in distributing the merchandise and facilitating the book signing event on the second day of the event. They were able to connect with representatives from SafeStack, Strava, Swimm, Vonage, Improving, Capital One, Flexiana, John Deere and many other companies about their newest inventions and products.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Abhilash and other students with Charles L.G. Comstock, one of the creators of the strange loop lemniscate sculpture" src="/assets/images/1695328700073-fb60cc3c833cc611c7541173fc5e49d2.jpeg" width="1170" height="878" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Lemniscate sculpture" src="/assets/images/lemniscate-15e460e63b85e319297d2c026c7689a0.png" width="1124" height="1334" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Elementary OS Workshop]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/elementary-os</link>
            <guid>elementary-os</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[We launched first monthly open source software workshop at the SLU Library's ATC. Students got a hands-on practice creating and using a portable Linux. It was a great success that exceeded the expectations of all the planners.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>We launched first monthly open source software workshop at the SLU Library's ATC. Students got a hands-on practice creating and using a portable Linux. It was a great success that exceeded the expectations of all the planners. </p><p><strong>What:</strong> Elementary OS<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> Presentedy by <a href="https://yashb196.github.io/yashb196/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Yash Bhatia</a>, MS student in Computer Science<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Friday, September 15<br>
1:30-2:30 p.m. (1 hour)<br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/library/services/academic-technology-commons/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Pius Library, ATC</a><br>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1QhlBWzoqiha1X8AogqNqMb4jynmaEDOAU2xmdrFD3Cc/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">presentation of instructions</a></p><p>A group of students and staff huddled over laptops around a large conference table in the Academic Technology Commons of Saint Louis University's Pius Library. The sound of 3D printers hummed in the background. On an already busy Friday afternoon these students had elected to spend their time getting some hands on experiences with open source software. </p><p>Yash Bhatia, a second year Masters student in Computer Science and a Research Assistant with Open Source with SLU, handed out USB flash drives and printed instructions. Then he went <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1QhlBWzoqiha1X8AogqNqMb4jynmaEDOAU2xmdrFD3Cc/edit?usp=sharing" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">step-by-step</a> with students down the path of creating a bootable flash drive with <a href="https://elementary.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">elementary OS</a>. Elementry OS is a distribution of the Linux OS that touts itself as "The thoughtful, capable, and ethical replacement for Windows and macOS". Yash then walked those attending the workshop through actually using the flash drive they created as a <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Live_USB" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">portable operating system</a>. This is a technique where the user can plug and play the entire system on any desktop computer. He walked the group through a variety of use cases for a portable OS, and showed some of elementaryOS's capabilities as a portable operating system.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Yash introduces elementary OS" src="/assets/images/20230915_003-8171ecc2dfc0647f654c323fb571e37a.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Students working together" src="/assets/images/20230915_001-2881c26eb854d018bc0ee7c8cf383aaf.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Yash explaining details" src="/assets/images/20230915_005-5012907a674e05044f954a2405745e39.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Students all around the table" src="/assets/images/20230915_002-914320b911fe98ddc238a0e4d9112faf.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="Yash assisting staff learning about OSS" src="/assets/images/20230915_004-1be527d5a895b5254d5a9dbff750aa3c.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q">
<img loading="lazy" alt="3D printers printing in the background; possibly still printing the same job today." src="/assets/images/20230915_000-bb10edb6d9d7a467176d4f3bcf5138a1.jpg" width="4080" height="3072" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[OSSci Panel Discussion - Accelerating Scientific Discovery]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/ossci-panel-discussion</link>
            <guid>ossci-panel-discussion</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Members from Open-Source Science (OSSci) were at Saint Louis University and our students had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members for discussion.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Members from Open-Source Science (OSSci) were at Saint Louis University and our students had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members for discussion.</p><p><strong>What:</strong> Hackathon<br>
<strong>Who:</strong> <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/abhilashkotha/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Abhilash Kotha</a>, student in MS Computer Science and graduate research assistant at Open Source with SLU and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/rajukarmuri731/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Raju Karmuri</a> alumni and tech lead at Open-Source at SLU were part of the discussion panel<br>
<strong>When:</strong> Monday, July 10 <br>
<strong>Where:</strong> <a href="https://www.slu.edu/admission/visit/index.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Saint Louis University</a>
<strong>Resources:</strong> <a href="https://opensource.science/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">OSSci Website</a></p><p>Students had an incredible time as they had an opportunity to be panelists and organizing members at the Open-Source Science (OSSci) event at St. Louis University! It was an inspiring conversation about accelerating scientific discovery through open-source science. Panelists Tim Holy, Alexy Khrabrov, Patrick Cuba, Abhilash Kotha, and Raju Karmuri had engaging discussions that shed light on many important topics the audience liked their conversation on how to bridge the communication gap between science and technical communities with more education and training, and how open source could help that.</p><p><a href="https://medium.com/open-source-science-initiative/st-louis-university-july-10-panel-discussion-accelerating-scientific-discovery-2285eb2bfb60" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ossci Newsletter</a></p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Discussion panel" src="/assets/images/panel-c02f3492ba9943aba3b94b4cb280278c.jpg" width="1400" height="1091" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Starting Up]]></title>
            <link>https://oss-slu.github.io/news/starting-up</link>
            <guid>starting-up</guid>
            <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Saint Louis University Computer Science Department starts and open source program office with a generous $704,482 grant from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Saint Louis University Computer Science Department starts and open source program office with a generous $704,482 grant from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation.</p><p>More details on our start can be found in <a href="https://www.slu.edu/news/2022/april/open-source-software-center.php" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SLU Newslink</a>.</p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>announcement</category>
            <category>news</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>